so here's another short
Suton except from a go drink I won polka
once 576 to 582 it's about the
mindfulness recollected nests of the
body mmm
so one thing because when developed and
cultivated leads to great anxiety leads
to great welfare leads to great security
from bondage leads to mindfulness and
awareness leads to acquisition of
knowledge and vision and leads to
pleasant dwelling here and now leads to
realization of the fruit of knowledge
and liberation which one thing
mindfulness of the body this because is
the one thing that which when developed
and cultivated leads to great anxiety
great welfare great security from
bondage and so on so you might wonder
here why it is a great anxiety great
concern it refers to when start
recognizing kind of the necessary
preconditions which is they certainly
recognition of the inevitability of
suffering for example and then that the
fact that you are not well you are
you're liable you're subjected to to
sickness aging and death all these
things they can before one's body they
will they would affect in and sometimes
even undermine your own life your
completely you remain completely liable
to those things so most people live
their life completely ignoring that
that's why when the Buddha went out of
his palace he referred to things you've
seen as divine messengers they were
basically conveying a message of a
certain reality that awaits every human
yet most people managed to sort of spend
their life pretty much covering covering
the very reality up so the first thing
is going to happen if you start
practicing mindfulness of the body
correctly is you can experience anxiety
but suddenly you are
rediscovering that the fact that you are
you're out there in the world you are
liable to these things you're not in
control and that the circumstances
elements are you fully subjected to it
you're like that means the velocity and
also do you like a flayed cow that being
consumed by if it leans on the wall for
support he gets eaten but in six days
and on the wall it lays down for support
gets in eaten but instead they're living
on the ground if it stands the one they
live in the air so on so so attending to
the to the maintaining that mindfulness
of the body correctly the recollection
is of the of the pretty much of the
nature of the body which is the nature
of that being subjected to illness being
subjected to two things that are that
you cannot possibly foresee so having
that at the arm on the back of your mind
as a certain context that you cultivate
will have to result in anxiety initially
at least because the anxiety it's a
symptom off of that cover-up if you
haven't been covering a certain reality
up in regard to things you you are
liable to you wouldn't be anxious about
it so anxiety is that is that sort of a
crack in that plaster that you have
applied on the under certain aspects of
existence that you refuse to admit
yourself because they are far too
unpleasant so in this in this suit in
particular it says that if you were to
cultivate then that mindfulness properly
to lead to to great anxiety more like a
great concern recognition of great
concern which is pretty much necessary
step for you to look for the way out if
you don't if you don't experience that
concern or as the Buddha would say or
even try and invoke in monks they're
called complacent and lazy sense of
urgency so you need to recognize that
time might be short your entire life the
way you know it things that they're to
you things that are not
to you everything your preferences your
sense desires things that you go through
on a daily basis all of that is there
undermined by the nature of the body
that you are not in control of so you
can think of it in terms of like your
your closed-in I mean a vehicle in a car
that it's running down the hill and
there are no brakes or maybe brakes work
limit like in a limited manner let's say
like that a bit more accurate so you can
slow down or not but you cannot
completely stop it's impossible you can
see you can mmm you can steer to the
left you can steer to the right you can
you can choose the direction but why do
you think what one thing you cannot do
is stop going downhill so that that's
pretty much the the human existence the
the life we are kind of living and
leading it's all heading in that certain
direction and there's nothing you can do
about it but most of the people and the
minds that are not untrained they are
unable to bear that recognition that you
are heading downhill one way or the
other doesn't matter how good how great
your life might be death is inevitable
aging is inevitable sickness is
inevitable so if you were to not lose
the sight of this context well there are
many things then that you would not do
in this life like you would not take for
granted your own senses the pleasure you
get from your own senses you will not
take for granted irritation and your
will you wouldn't be acting out of it
that's what what I said in or maybe was
in the Buddha but it was in the
Dhammapada it was said that people who quarrel and
it was said that people who quarrel and
bear grudges I'm kind of paraphrasing
people who quarrel and bear grudges are
the ones that forget that that in this
world we are all condemned to die as in
if you were to not forget the ultimate
the direction that that vehicle car is
heading you just you it would be
impossible for you to bear a grudge so
whenever you find yourself bearing
grudges a real will or chasing
sensuality that can only be done
on a with a on a on a basis of ignoring
the fact that you're liable to death and
the death is inevitable that's why one
of the the chief of the mindfulness that
you can practice is is mindfulness of
death which is closely obviously it's
inseparable from mindfulness of the body
it results in the same recognitions so
that's how it would lead to great
anxiety the useful anxiety the anxiety
that can then reveal the cover-up and
because of that you seek your own
welfare if you keep doing it you stop
feeling anxious because you stop
covering it up so then it will lead to
your great welfare then furthermore it
will lead to the security from bondage
in this particular meaning is security
from bondage basically things that bind
you are things that then you find the
Ihram pleasing to you so they don't
direct they don't bind you directly so
to speak so it's not the fault of the
things that you are bound by them it's
the fault of you valuing the pleasure
that you get through those things thus
those things become your bond so if you
were to approve to the value of pleasure
you have sever the bond and you would do
that if you practice if you maintain
that recollection is of the context of
your body correctly and when I say the
body I don't mean sensations of your
body and so on that you might be
attending to means context of the body
the nature of the body what is the body
liable to what are the characteristics
of the body
what is the worry what are the
implications of having body well its
liability to sickness aging and death
liability to elements having to endure
them liability to hot/cold abusive
experiences words under are unpleasant
to hear basically being devoured by the
senses and pressured by the senses that
is the nature of the body so when when
you when when we say mindfulness to the
body were recollecting so the body that
is what you must keep recollected and be
mindful of not I'm touching my feeling
feeling and feeling things my back
that is actually stands for the body nor
is it even a recollectionist of the body
just literally focusing on the tactile
aspects of your present experience as a
whole that's one of the people miss
misconstrue the whole idea of sensations
and some how they're feeling they're not
sensations that you observe through the
trial your body are basically tactile
like your attention following the
tactile directions that's it so an
account of touch you somehow can become
an arahant impossible mindfulness of the
modi means body is a unit but is a whole
things that regardless of sight sound
smell taste touch things that you are
liable to which is sickness aging death
non control impermanence all of that so
that's why by severing that bondage it
would leave to that it would lead to
that establishment of composure of
Samadhi through that mindfulness and
awareness which then leads to like
thoroughly completely uncovering
anything you've been covering up freeing
yourself from the contradictions of
desires your will and so on leads to the
acquisition of knowledge and vision
which leads to pleasant abiding right
here right now as in Pleasant abiding
means ease you're free from bondage free
from pressure free from anxiety means
you're at ease you have you lay down the
burden you're completely free which is
exactly what leads them to realization
of the fruit of that knowledge and
liberation uh turn shape so so that in
that sense like if you practice
mindfulness of the body that and also
you can see how it will then result in
knowledge because it's not just a random
technique that you're observing your
body how it moves or how it sets no
you're dwelling on the aspects of the
body that kind of well certainly direct
and they signify your whole life like
you know if you're ignoring video that
you liable to sickness aging and death
that is your context like ignoring the
certain truths so that's why you would
commit to various things in life be
bound by them change them obviously
implying that they will last forever
ignoring the fact that they can't so
that direct result of you not having the
direct result of you not having the
proper context of your body so if on the
other hand you were to change change the
background of that context and start
dwelling on things that are life that
the body is liable to then that will
have to then shape your other decisions
on a smaller scale you would not
possibly make careless choices and
decision out of the careful context it's
impossible that's why context is all that
that's why context is all that
mindfulness is fundamental in what
context is practicing mindfulness is
practicing the clarification of the
context and that's why it's you can't
have too much of that you can't be too
clear about the context that you are
liable to the context of your existence
you can have too much focusing you can
have too much of non focusing be too too
slack but you cannot have too much of
clarity in regard to the context of your
body is just impossible and the more the
clearer you are the more of the
knowledge and recognition gets
established and the more of the proper
Samadhi you develop because now you're
somebody's unshakable because the
recognition of what the the nature of
the body is you cannot forget because
how could you forget because any
experience you have is within the these
five senses within these five senses and
the mind of course so it's within the
body strictly speaking and that's what we
strictly speaking and that's what we
meant the body is the universe for you
there is nothing outside that you could
perceive or even concede so the extent
the extent of the universe is the extent
of the body the entire universe is
contained in this body less than two
meters tall as the buddha said it so if
you were to clarify the context of that
universe the certain characteristics of
impermanence characteristics of that
lack of satisfaction you would not be
able to basically maintain all the
things they depend upon those
characteristics not being clarified such
as sensuality ill-will anger
carelessness indolence and pretty much
everything else that's by definition and
also